<oai_dc:dc xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
    xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
    xmlns:srw_dc="info:srw/schema/1/dc-schema"
    xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/"
    xmlns:etdms="http://www.ndltd.org/standards/metadata/etdms/1.0/"
    xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
    <dc:title>A Boron Alkylidene-Alkene Cycloaddition Reaction: Application to the Synthesis of Aphanamal</dc:title>
    <dc:creator>Deaton, Timothy Maxwell</dc:creator>
    <dc:contributor>McAuthor, Second</dc:contributor>
    <dc:description>Thesis advisor: Morken, James P.</dc:description>
    <dc:description>Thesis advisor: McAdvisor, Secondy</dc:description>
    <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
    <dc:type>Electronic Thesis or Dissertation</dc:type>
    <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
    <dc:type>thesis</dc:type>
    <dc:date>2017</dc:date>
    <dc:publisher>Boston College</dc:publisher>
    <dc:type>monographic</dc:type>
    <dc:language>English</dc:language>
    <dc:format>electronic</dc:format>
    <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
    <dc:description>Described herein is the exploration of a novel methodology whereby boronate-ester bearing cyclopentanes are produced by reaction between an unactivated olefin and what is described as a boron alkylidene. The mechanism is evaluated and concluded to proceed through a boracyclic intermediate that is achieved by a closed-shell, carbanion addition to the olefin. This mechanistic conclusion is arrived upon by considering two likely alternative routes (an open-shell, radical cyclization and a [2+2] concerted process) and providing evidence to refute them. A reaction scope is established as well as the utility of the methodology through the racemic synthesis of a natural sesquiterpene: aphanamal. Finally, the future of the reaction development will be considered by providing a single example of a 6-endo cyclization.</dc:description>
    <dc:subject>Boron</dc:subject>
    <dc:subject>seconds topic</dc:subject>
    <dc:subject>Cyclopentane</dc:subject>
    <dc:subject>Methodology</dc:subject>
    <dc:subject>Synthesis</dc:subject>
    <dc:coverage>Chestnut Hill</dc:coverage>
    <dc:rights>Copyright is held by the author, with all rights reserved, unless otherwise noted.</dc:rights>
    <dc:description>Thesis (MS) — Boston College, 2017.</dc:description>
    <dc:description>Submitted to: Boston College. Graduate School of Arts and Sciences.</dc:description>
    <dc:description>Discipline: Chemistry.</dc:description>
    <dc:identifier>http://hdl.handle.net/2345/bc-ir:107597</dc:identifier>
</oai_dc:dc>