<oai_dc:dc xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
    xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
    xmlns:srw_dc="info:srw/schema/1/dc-schema"
    xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/"
    xmlns:etdms="http://www.ndltd.org/standards/metadata/etdms/1.0/"
    xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
    <dc:title>Interview with Stuart Joel Hecht on Transposing Broadway: Jews, assimilation, and the American musical, by Stuart Joel Hecht</dc:title>
    <dc:creator>Hecht, Stuart Joel, 1955-</dc:creator>
    <dc:contributor>Rapple, Brendan Alphonso, 1949-</dc:contributor>
    <dc:type>MovingImage</dc:type>
    <dc:type>interview</dc:type>
    <dc:date>2012</dc:date>
    <dc:type>monographic</dc:type>
    <dc:language>English</dc:language>
    <dc:format>34 min., 39 sec.</dc:format>
    <dc:format>electronic</dc:format>
    <dc:format>video/mp4</dc:format>
    <dc:description>Over the last hundred years, musical theatre artists - from Berlin to Rodgers and Hammerstein to Sondheim - have developed a form that corresponds directly to the Americanization of the increasingly Jewish New York audience; and that audience's aspirations and concerns have played out in the shows themselves. Musicals thus became a paradigm which instructed newcomers in how to assimilate while correspondingly envisioning "American Dream" America as democratic and inclusive. Broadway musicals still continue to function today as "cultural Ellis Islands" for fringe populations seeking acceptance into the nation's mainstream - including women, blacks, Latinos, and gays - all essentially modeled upon the Jewish example. Stuart J. Hecht offers a fascinating examination of the relationship between Jews, assimilation, and the changing face of the American musical.</dc:description>
    <dc:description>Title supplied by cataloger.</dc:description>
    <dc:relation>aNonsort Transposing Broadway: test subtitle</dc:relation>
    <dc:relation>Faculty publication highlights -- second series</dc:relation>
    <dc:rights>Use of this resource is governed by the terms and conditions of the Creative Commons license "Attribution-NonCommercial 3.0 Unported (CC BY-NC 3.0)." (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/)</dc:rights>
    <dc:subject>Musicals -- United States -- History -- 20th century</dc:subject>
    <dc:subject>Musicals</dc:subject>
    <dc:coverage>United States</dc:coverage>
    <dc:identifier>http://hdl.handle.net/2345/3171</dc:identifier>
</oai_dc:dc>